Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York Chapter; Records apap078
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York Chapter Records
1967-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York Chapter
apap078
0.53 cubic ft.
The materials in the Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York Chapter collection document the chapter's early activities and establishment.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Conservative Party of New York State donated all items in this collection.
Biographical History
Americans for Effective Law Enforcement was founded in 1966 as a non-profit corporation for the purpose of establishing an "organized voice" for citizens regarding the country's crime problem, and to lend support to professional law enforcement agencies. The organization also works to pressure for more efficient law enforcement through court action and information campaigns. The group became functional in early 1967 after receiving a tax-exempt ruling from the IRS. The first project undertaken was the filing of a friend of the court or amicus curiae brief in the Supreme Court. The New York Chapter was based in New York City and organized in the early 1970s. LeRoy Marceau became Executive Director of the state chapter in 1972.
Scope and Contents
The materials in the Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York Chapter collection document the chapter's early days through the by-laws, articles of incorporation, and constitution. The collection includes material from the period when LeRoy Marceau was Executive Director of the state chapter beginning in 1972. The collection is particularly strong in documenting the New York Chapter's solicitation for funding from individuals, corporations, and foundations when the New York Chapter was first organized. There is also correspondence with potential donors and officials from the Americans for Effective Law Enforcement national office in Evanston, Illinois. The collection includes research material from issues of interest to the organization such as school discipline, busing school children in the 1970s to create integrated schools, the bail system in New York City, and other related issues. The Legal briefs are some of the court cases for which the organization filed friends of the court, or amicus curiae, briefs. Alert was a publication of the national Americans for Effective Law Enforcement and it contains information about the activities of the state chapters and contemporary issues of interest.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Criminal Justice and Prisons; Criminal justice, Administration of--New York (State); Police--Political activity--New York (State); Correspondence; Files by subject; Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York Chapter; Americans for Effective Law Enforcement
- American Bar Association Committees, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 1)
- American Civil Liberties Union, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 2)
- Advisory Committee, Undated (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 3)
- Alert, 1970; 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 4)
- Annual Report, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 5)
- Arbitration Group, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 6)
- Arizona Chapter, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 7)
- Articles of Incorporation and By-laws, 1967 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 8)
- Board of Directors, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 9)
- Budget, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 10)
- Charter, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 11)
- Conference Board, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 12)
- Constitution, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 14)
- IRS Qualification, 1967; 1970 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 15)
- Long Range Plan, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 16)
- Members, 1971 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 17)
- News Clippings, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 18)
- Prospectus and Budget, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 19)
- Promotion Kit, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 20)
- Solicitation, Corporate, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 21)
- Solicitation, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 22)
- Solicitation, Foundations, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 23)
- Solicitation, New York State, 1972 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 24)
- State Chapter Conference, 1973 (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 25)
- State Chapter Manual, Undated (Box 1 (Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, New York ), Folder 26)